Finding Aid for the Bern Porter Papers, 1935-1983
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Bern Porter Papers,
1935-1983
639
Porter, Bern, 1911-
100 boxes (50 linear ft.) 5 oversize boxes
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Bernard Harden Porter (1911- )was the Republican candidate for governor of Maine (1969) and was an author, poet, editor, illustrator, and publisher. The collection includes papers, correspondence, manuscripts, notes, books, printed items, ephemera, a film, illustrations, portraits, and lithographs by, and relating to, Bern Porter.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
PARTIALLY PROCESSED COLLECTION UNAVAILABLE FOR USE: except for boxes 1, 37, 39, 41-43, 95-98, 103-105. Inquiries regarding these materials should be directed, in writing, to the Manuscripts Librarian, UCLA Dept. of Special Collections.
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Additional Physical Form Available
A copy of the original version of this online finding aid is available at the UCLA Department of Special Collections for in-house consultation and may be obtained for a fee. Please contact:
Public Services Division
UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections
Room A1713, Charles E. Young Research Library
Box 951575
Los Angeles, CA 90095-1575
Telephone: 310/825-4988 (10:00 a.m. - 4:45 p.m., Pacific Time)
Email: spec-coll@library.ucla.edu
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4233602
Biography
Bernard Harden Porter was born on February 14, 1911 in Porter Settlement, Maine; Sc.B, Colby College, 1932; Sc.M, Brown University, 1933; special courses at Da Vinci School (1937), Convair School (1957), University of Maine (1960), and Federal School (1963); in 1929 founded Bern Porter (publishing company) in Belfast, Maine; became physicist for Acheson Colloids Corporation (1935-40) and for the Manhattan District Engineers (1940-45); became consulting physicist in 1945; director of Contemporary Gallery, West Coast Design Guild, and Fund for Contemporary Expression, 1947-50; Republican candidate for governor of Maine, 1969; became author, poet, editor, illustrator, and publisher; founding fellow, International Poetry Society; published works include Colloidal Graphite: its Properties and Applications (1939), Map of Physics (1939), Henry Miller: a Bibliography (compiler, 1943), Scandinavian Summer (1961), Wernher Von Braun: a Bibliography and Selected Papers (editor, 1966), Reminiscences, 1927-1970 (1970), American Strange (1979), and Isla Vista (1981).
Scope and Content
Boxes 1, 37, 39, 41-43, 95-98, and 103-105 include papers, correspondence, manuscripts, notes, books, printed items, ephemera, a film, illustrations, portraits, and lithographs by and relating to Bern Porter. Manuscripts include Man (1965) by William Faulkner (edited by Porter), Semblance of a Devoted Past, What To Do About Alf, and Verda: The Master Builder by Henry Miller, and an essay, poems, and Run on by Porter. Also includes a portrait of James Joyce, a portrait of Porter by Liesel Rosenthal, three lithographs, and one oil painting.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Porter, Bern, 1911- --Archives.; Physicists--United States--Archival resources.; Poets, American--20th century--Archival resources.; Authors, American--20th century--Archival resources.; Publishers and publishing--United States--Archival resources.
Container List
- [Huntsville, Alabama]
  [No further description available]
  - Through January 1966., 1 folder. (Box 45)
  - Through May 15, 1966., 1 folder. (Box 45)
  - Through July 20, 1966., 1 folder. (Box 47)
  - December 1966., 1 folder. (Box 48)
  - To February 15, 1967., 1 folder. (Box 49)
  - To June 15, 1967., 1 folder. (Box 49)
    Includes Ole.
  - To October 1, 1967., 1 folder. (Box 50)
  - To November 1, 1967., 1 folder. (Box 50)
  - Dated November 10, 1965. (Box 44)
  - To departure for Guatemala. February 25, 1968., 2 folders. (Box 52)
- [Bernard Porter]
  - Folio. (Box 42)
  - Folder. (Box 43)
  - Distributed by Bernard Porter--his early authors., Envelope. (Box 43)
  - Bibliographical notes. November 1971-January 1977. (Box 96)
- [Illustrations by Bernard Porter]
  - Folder no.2: Marijuana Review no.2. (Box 57)
  - Drawing. 1961. By Bernard Porter. (Box 75)
    Case by Bernard Porter.
  - Original illustrations for Taifun Willi. (Box 75)
  - Original illustrations for Lamantia's erotic poems. Run-on by Bern Porter., Original manuscript. (Box 93)
  - Letter. John G. Moore. vol.1, illustrated by Bernard Porter. (Box 51)
  - Dawnbird., Original cut. (Box 66)
- [Miscellaneous]
  - March 15, 1972-October 15, 1972., Folders. (Box 81)
  - March 15, 1972-October 15, 1972., Folders. (Box 82)
  - October 15, 1972-January 1, 1973., Folder. (Box 84)
  - January 1, 1973-June 1, 1973., Folder. (Box 85)
  - June 1, 1973-October 15, 1973., Folder. (Box 85)
  - no.1-2: Correspondence, notes, manuscript material and little magazines. October 1973-December 1973., 2 folders. (Box 90)
  - Correspondence, notes, manuscript material and little magazines. January 1974-April 1975., 2 folders. (Box 91)
  - Bay Area Creators. 1945-1965. (Box 43)
  - [Miscellaneous]., 1 folder. (Box 48)
    Frank Lobdell Catalog. Faulkner Poetry Project. Production material for Art Productions. 1928-1965. Correspondence with W. Lowenfels.
  - #7. May 1967. Contains reviews of seven Porter publications. (Box 49)
  - Folder no.1: Guatemala City. February 26, 1968-April 27, 1968. (Box 53)
  - Folder no.2: Guatemala City and Rockland, Maine. April 1968-May 2, 1968. (Box 53)
  - Summary of Knox County Regional Report. 1969. (Box 61)
  - Cell 666: A television script by Eve Linkletter, Clinton Dufy and Bern Porter. (Box 94)
  - February 20, 1977-October 2, 1978., 1 folder. (Box 97)
  - Vagabond White Paper, no.5 (c. 1983). (Box 98)
    Contains interview with Bern Porter by Phil Nuremberg. Signed by Porter and Nuremberg.
  - Portrait of James Joyce., Framed and boxed. (Box 103)
    A coloured photograph, part of Porter's Joyce collection which did not go to Colby College, Maine.
  - Unprocessed additions. (Box 99-100)
    Purchase, ca. 1986(?).
- [Edited by Bernard Porter]
  - Leaves Fall. Fred Luigel and Bernard Porter, editors., Complete file, autographed. [Photocopy]. (Box 42)
  - Henry: Anthology of World Poets, edited by Bernard Porter., Manuscript. (Box 66)
- [Published / Distributed by Bernard Porter]
  - Recent Selected Articles by Buckminster Fuller. Introduction autographed by Gertz. Distributed by Bern Porter Books. (Box 51)
  - Bernard Langlais, by P.L. Ely. (Box 61)
  - A Bridge for Luxembourg, by Paolo Soleri. Pasadena California: Bern Porter. 1958., 7 sheets. (Box 104)
  - 3 lithographs and 1 oil painting by George Stliilman. Pasadena, California: Bern Porter. 1958., 4 items. (Box 105)
  - The Genesis of `The Tropic of Cancer', by Michael Fraenkel. Additions by Bernard Porter. Published by Bernard Porter in 1970. (Box 65)
- [Photographs / Portraits of Bernard Porter]
  - Portrait of Bernard Porter by Imogen Cunningham. (Box 41)
  - Bernard Porter at Schillerhaus Gardens by H. Bowden. Sausalito, California. August 12, 1950., Original copperplate. (Box 41)
  - Photograph of Bern Porter, by Harry Bowden. San Francisco. ca. 1950. (Box 88)
  - Portrait of Bernard Porter., Original cut. (Box 66)
  - Portrait of Bern Porter by Liesel Rosenthal. (Box 103)
- [Works by Others]
  - Wildcat Hall Revisited: A Photographic Visit With Edward Weston, by H. Bowden., Film. (Box 66)
  - Fifty-six Preliminary Poems. Lee Ver Duft. (Box 51)
  - Lyrics & Epigrams. Dakin Laurence, translator. (Box 37)
  - Man. William Faulkner. 1965., Manuscript. (Box 41)
  - Bibliography of Henry Miller. Maxine Renken. Denver. 1962. (Box 44)
  - Copley-Book. Diter Rot. 1965. (Box 51)
  - Cancer on Trial. E.R. Hutchison. (Box 51)
    Insert by Bernard Porter.
  - Folder no.3: Letters, manuscripts, early pamphlet publications of Dutch-American poet Lee Ver Duft, etc. (Box 58)
  - Pop Art. Do it yourself. (Box 72)
  - Semblance of a Devoted Past, by Henry Miller., Manuscript. (Box 75)
  - What to do About Alf, by Henry Miller., Manuscript. (Box 76)
  - Metaphor: an Annotated Bibliography and History, by Warren Shibles. Whitewater, Wisconsin: Language Press, c. 1971. (Box 76)
  - Varda: the Master Builder, by Henry Miller., Manuscript. (Box 77)
    With Bernard Porter drawings.
  - Bibliography. Janelle-Therese Viglini. Manuscripts. Poetry. Where to go / What to do in New York. (Box 95)
  - Easy Dream Book, by Toby Messman. Piedmont, California, Bernard Porter Books. October 1972., Copy number one. (Box 83)
  - Pregnant Man, 4: Still Life (1971-1972), by Simon Fallon. n.p.,. ca. 1972., Original typescript. (Box 83)
- [Belfast, Maine]
  - April 1, 1975-May 6, 1976., 1 folder. (Box 92)
  - May 6, 1976-September 7, 1976., 1 folder. (Box 92)
  - September 7, 1976-February 20, 1977., 1 folder. (Box 93)
- [Rockland, Maine]
  - To September 1968., 1 folder. (Box 51)
    Letters from Ginsburg, Rockwell Kent, etc.
  - no.3: June 1968. (Box 54)
  - no.4: through July 1, 1968. (Box 54)
  - no.1-2: Summer 1968. (Box 55)
  - no.1-2: Fall 1968. (Box 56)
  - no.1: September 1968-March 1969. (Box 57)
  - no.1: January 1969-July 1969. (Box 59)
    Production materials include correspondence for Dieresis by Bernard Porter and Man by William Faulkner.
  - no.2: April-June 1969. (Box 59)
    John Martin (Black Sparrow Press), Dick Higgins (Something Else Press).
  - no.3: June-July 1969. (Box 60)
    Issues of the time: Berkeley Barb, New York Free Press, Village Voice, etc.
  - July 1969., 1 folder. (Box 60)
    Contains Bernard Porter bibliography.
  - July-August, 1969., 1 folder. (Box 62)
  - August 1969-December 1969., 1 folder. (Box 62)
  - January 1970., 4 folders. (Box 63-64)
  - February 1970-March 1970., 1 folder. (Box 65)
  - May-June, 1970., 1 folder. (Box 67)
  - June 1970., 1 folder. (Box 67)
  - August 1970-December 1970., 1 folder. (Box 68)
    Contains Bernard Porter lecture: Aspects of the Atomic Bomb, October 10, 1970, and correspondence.
  - July 1970., 1 folder. (Box 68)
  - January 1971., 1 folder. (Box 73)
  - February 1971-March 1971., 1 folder. (Box 73)
  - April 1971-May 1971., 1 folder. (Box 74)
  - Through June 1, 1971., 1 folder. (Box 74)
  - Bernard Porter: Bibliography. August 30, 1969-October 2, 1971. Rockland, Maine. January 11, 1972., Only copy. (Box 77)
  - Through August 1, 1971. (Box 78)
  - Through January 1, 1972. (Box 79)
  - Through January 1, 1972. (Box 80)
  - Through March 15, 1972. (Box 80)
  - Through March 15, 1972. (Box 81)
- [The Viglini Letters]
  - vol.1. February 1973-June 1974. Bern Porter. 1977. (Box 94)
  - vol.2. July 1974-February 1977. Bern Porter. 1977. (Box 95)
  - vol.3. March 1977-February 1979. (Box 97)
  - The Viglini Manuscripts. (Box 96)
- [By Bernard Porter]
  - Artifacts. (Box 1)
  - Cosmic Sight. (Box 39)
  - Alollo. (Box 41)
  - Miller Said., Original. (Box 42)
  - Art productions. 1937. New York. 1937., 80 leaves in a cloth case. (Box 104)
    Collected and assembled by Bern Porter.
  - Broadside. San Francisco. 1955-58., 1 folder. (Box 105)
    Complete file of 52 numbered items, and negatives of most of them. Also included are a few projected broadsides, never published. Photographed in March, 1976, Matt Lubic, Seattle, Washington, in order to publish them in facsimile.
  - Art Scrapbook. (Box 102)
    Collected, assembled and with a front cover in oil, by Bernard Porter (On loan).
  - After Brockman: A Symposium. n.p., Abyss Publications. 1974. (Box 88)
    With typescript manuscript of essay by Bern Porter (inserted).
  - Contemporary Italian Artists, compiled by Bern Porter. Venice. 1973., Copy 1 of 2 copies. (Box 88)
  - Per Book. Rockland, Maine. 1970., Copy number one. (Box 69)
  - Enry One. Rockland, Maine. 1970., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - Enry 2-5. Rockland, Maine. 1970., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - OEye. Rockland, Maine. 1970., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - Reminiscences, 1927-1970. Rockland, Maine. 1970., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - Moscow. 1966., Only copy. (Box 46)
  - 468B. 1966., One of six copies. (Box 46)
  - Maldorot., Only copy. (Box 46)
    With original frontispiece by Bernard Porter.
  - My life in New Hampshire. 1961., 1 folder. (Box 46)
    A collection of papers.
  - Mathematics for Electronics. Englewood Cliffs: Prentice Hall. 1965. (Box 46)
  - Knox County, Maine., Holograph. (Box 58)
  - Knox County, Maine. A Regional Report. 1969. (Box 61)
  - The Box. (Box 61)
  - Soda 19. (Box 61)
  - Recollections of Alabama., Copper plate. (Box 65)
  - Oraisons Fanèbres de Bossuet. (Box 65)
  - Novel Art News., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - Ula. 1971., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - b.p. 1971., Only copy. (Box 69)
  - Package no.1: Assorted Cuts, 1938-1965. vol.1., Only copy. (Box 70)
    Porter also made the case by hand.
  - Assorted Cuts, 1935-1965. vol.2, by Bernard Porter., Only copy. (Box 70)
  - Package no.2: Assorted Cuts, 1949-1965. vol.3., Only copy. (Box 70)
  - Assorted Cuts, 1961-1967. vol.4., Only copy. (Box 71)
  - Assorted Cuts, 1945-1965. vol.5., Only copy. (Box 71)
  - Assorted Cuts, 1965. vol.6., Only copy. (Box 71)
  - Cut Leaves. (Box 72)
  - Day Notes for Mother. (Box 72)
  - Ginsberg/Porter., Only copy. (Box 72)
  - Hexa 914., Only copy. (Box 72)
  - Knox County Diary., 1 folder. (Box 75)
  - I've Left., Paperback. (Box 76)
  - Construction. 1961. (Box 76)
  - Mechanical Drawing. (Box 76)
  - Found Painting. 1963., Only copy. (Box 77)
  - Frosted 1C27. 1971., Only copy. (Box 77)
  - The 14th of February. 1971., Only copy. (Box 78)
  - Found Poems. Millerton, New York: Something Else Press. 1972. (Box 81)
    Paperback edition with holograph notes and signature.
  - Founds, vol.3. n.p. n.d. (Box 83)
  - Hand Fashioned Chocolates. n.p.,. ca. 1972., Only copy. (Box 84)
  - Founds, vol.1. 1968-1972., Only copy. (Box 86)
  - Mothering Time: Selected Works. 1928-1973. Published by Black Sparrow Press: Los Angeles. 1973., Original typescript. (Box 86)
  - Founds, vol.2. 1968-1972., Only copy. (Box 87)
  - Trattoria Due Forni., First of two copies. (Box 87)
  - Where to go / what to do / when in New York / week of June 12, 1972, by Bern Porter. n.p. 1973., Copy 146 of 250 copies. (Box 88)
  - no.1: Life in Alabama., 1 folder. (Box 88)
  - no.2: Life in Alabama., 1 folder. (Box 89)
  - no.3: Life in Alabama., 1 folder. (Box 89)
  - Found Object. 1946., Only copy. (Box 101)
    Case by Bernard Porter, 1971.
  - The Manhattan telephone book. (Box 98)
  - Poems. 1984., Holograph and photocopy. (Box 98)
    Written on this around-the-world trip. January-March 1984.